Guide to the Yale Collection of Herbert Matter
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Yale Collection of Herbert Matter
1928-1991
MS 1630
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
4
The collection consists of client files and biographical material related to Herbert Matter. The client files provide examples of Matter's logo, advertisement, and publication designs for several well known businesses, including Knoll, Inc., Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum, and the New Haven Railroad. The biographical material contains both works created by Matter, such as promotional material and photographs, as well as works about Matter, such as published articles and papers related to his teaching career at Yale. The majority of materials in this collection were amassed in support of a retrospective exhibition which took place at the Yale University Art and Architecture Gallery from January 16 to February 3, 1978.
Matter, Herbert, 1907-1984
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Yale Art Gallery, 1991. Gift of Knoll, Inc., 1992.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exists must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series: I. Client Files, 1932-1974. II. Biographical Material, 1928-1991.
Scope and Contents
The Yale Collection of Herbert Matter contains materials that trace the personal and professional aspects of the life of an important graphic designer. The collection will be of interest to those studying the design career of Matter, the history of advertising or logos for the companies represented (especially Knoll, Inc.), the publications of the Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum, and to some extent, the life history of Matter.
The collection primarily focuses on Matter's work with clients, especially the magazine ads and promotional material he designed for Knoll between 1946 and 1966 and the publications he designed for the Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum from 1959 to 1967. The biographical material includes both copies of his Paris diaries from 1928 to 1932 and copies of notes on an exhibition about Matter which took place in 1989. Other notable items in the collection are photograms created in a Yale class, and some photographs taken by Matter studying the value contrasts of tree bark. The majority of materials in this collection were amassed in support of a retrospective exhibition which took place at the Yale University Art and Architecture Gallery from January 16 to February 3, 1978.
Biographical / Historical
Herbert Matter was born in Engelberg, Switzerland, on April 25, 1907. He was encouraged by his family to pursue his artistic interests, which were apparent early in his life. The Matter family owned a dance hall and restaurant where they hung Matter's early paintings.
In the late 1920s Matter moved to Paris to be a part of the active art scene there. He studied with the painters Fernand Léger and Amédée Ozenfant. He also assisted the graphic designer Adolphe Cassandre and the architect Le Corbusier. During his time in Paris, Matter started to move away from painting toward the graphic arts, especially photography, and he became a master of photomontage. Matter used this technique to great effect in several travel posters created between 1932 and 1936 for the Swiss National Tourist Office. This work established his reputation as a prominent and successful graphic designer.
Matter moved to New York City in 1936. He worked as photographer and designer for such magazines as Harper's Bazaar and Vogue and for lesser known, but more cutting edge, publications like New Pencil Points. He also designed publications for the Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum and the Museum of Fine Arts in Houston, Texas, as well as logos, publications, and advertising materials for many companies, most notably the New Haven Railroad and Knoll, Inc.
In 1952 Matter joined the faculty of the graphic design and photography programs at Yale University, where he taught until 1976. Matter was also involved with the New York Studio School, which his wife founded. As the Yale graduate program produced many successful designers, Matter's ideas became widespread in the graphic design world. Students remember Matter fondly and were greatly influenced by his teachings.
Matter died in Southampton, New York, on May 8, 1984.
Graphic arts; Matter, Herbert, 1907-1984; Knoll International, Inc; Yale University -- Faculty
- Client Files, 1932-1974; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains examples of design work produced by Matter, and is arranged alphabetically by client. Materials include photography, magazine advertisements, promotional material, publication design, and more. When the work that Matter produced for the client is merely a logo (as with the Boston and Maine or New Haven Railroads) the materials in these files are not necessarily produced by Matter, but do document the use of his logo designs. If Matter worked as a designer for a client, a publication from that client may be included, even if Matter's individual work is not specifically identified within the publication. Additionally, the Knoll file contains a selection of copper plates (color separated) that were used to print the advertisements Matter designed.
  - Acrilan, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Aluminum Company of America, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Awixa Pond Art Center, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Boston and Maine Railroad, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Container Corporation of America, [1959] (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - DuPont, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Evans Products Company, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum
    - Catalogs
      - "Accessions and Proposals", 1964 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - "American Abstract Expressionists and Imagists", 1961 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - "American Drawings", [1963] (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - "Francis Bacon", 1963 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - "Alexander Calder: A Retrospective Exhibition", 1964 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - "Joseph Cornell", 1967 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - "Jean Dubuffet 1962-66", 1966 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - "Elements of Modern Painting", 1961 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - "European Drawings", [after 1963] (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - "Guggenheim International Award 1964" (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - "Philip Guston", 1962 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - "Inaugural Selection", 1959 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - "Vasily Kandinsky 1966-1944: A Retrospective Exhibition", 1962 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - "Frederick Kiesler: Environmental Sculpture", 1964 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - "Paul Klee 1879-1940: A Retrospective Exhibition", 1967 (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - "Jan Muller 1922-1958", 1962 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - "Edward Munch", 1965 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - "One Hundred Paintings from the G. David Thompson Collection", 1961 (Box 2, Folder 25)
      - "Paintings from the Collection of the Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum", 1965 (Box 2, Folder 26)
      - "Antoni Tàpies", 1962 (Box 2, Folder 27)
      - "Jean Xceron", 1965 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Pamphlets
      - "Gauguin and the Decorative Style", 1966 (Box 2, Folder 29)
      - "Modern Masters from the collection of the Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum", 1961 (Box 2, Folder 30)
      - "Six Painters and the Object", 1963 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Posters, 1961-1974 (Box 2, Folder 32)
      General
      See also: Oversize folder 7
  - Harper's Bazaar, 1940
    General note
    See: Oversize Folder 5
  - House and Garden, 1948-[1950s] (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Kimbe Optic, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Knoll, Inc.
    - Advertisements, [1946-1966] (Box 2, Folder 35 - 37)
      See also: Oversize folder 4
    - Printing plates [copper], [1946-1966] (Box 3)
    - Printing plates [copper], [1946-1966] (Box 4)
    - Printing plates [copper], [1946-1966] (Box 5)
    - Printing plates [copper], [1946-1966] (Box 6)
    - Printing plates [copper], [1946-1966] (Box 7)
    - Printing plates [copper], [1946-1966] (Box 8)
    - Printing plates [copper], [1946-1966] (Box 9)
    - Printing plates [copper], [1946-1966] (Box 10)
    - Promotional materials, [1946-1966] (Box 11, Folder 38)
  - Matter, Alex [son], after 1966
    See: Oversize Folder 8
  - Morton Salt, undated (Box 11, Folder 39)
  - Museum of Fine Arts, Houston
    - Administrative publications
      - Annual Report, 1966 (Box 11, Folder 40)
      - Newsletter, 1964 (Box 11, Folder 41)
    - Catalogs
      - "Alberto Burri", 1963 (Box 11, Folder 42)
      - "Alexander Calder: Circus Drawings, Wire Sculpture and Toys", 1964 (Box 11, Folder 43)
      - "Eduardo Chillida", 1966 (Box 11, Folder 44)
      - "The Olmec Tradition", 1963 (Box 11, Folder 45)
    - Pamphlets
      - "Derain before 1915", 1962 (Box 11, Folder 46)
      - "Six Master Paintings Two Glasses On Sculpture", 1963 (Box 11, Folder 47)
      - "Some Recent Accessions 1961-1963" (Box 11, Folder 48)
  - The Museum School of Art, Houston, 1963 (Box 11, Folder 49)
  - New Haven Railroad, [ca.1954] (Box 11, Folder 50)
  - New Pencil Points, 1943 (Box 11, Folder 51)
  - New York Studio School, undated (Box 11, Folder 52)
    See also: Oversize Folder 6
  - Oxford Paper Company, undated (Box 11, Folder 53)
  - Reynolds Aluminum, undated (Box 11, Folder 54)
  - Swiss National Tourist Office, [1932-1936] (Box 11, Folder 55)
  - Upjohn Company/Medrol, undated (Box 11, Folder 56)
  - Vogue, 1950-1957 (Box 11, Folder 57)
  - Wilson, Morris, Crane and Anderson, [after 1967] (Box 11, Folder 58)
  - Unidentified clients, undated (Box 11, Folder 59)
  - Unidentified images, undated (Box 11, Folder 60)
- Biographical Material, 1928-1991; Series II
  The series contains a wide range of material both by and about Matter. Items created by Matter include photographs, a diary written during his stay in Paris, correspondence about grants, press sheets for a book on Giacometti, and promotional material for himself. The items about Matter include articles, correspondence, notes concerning exhibitions, photographs, and postcards. Original tapes and duplicating masters in boxes 13-14 may not be played. For information on copies created for research use consult the reference archivist.
  - Article on Matter ["Art in Industry" by Perey Seitlin], undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - A4 Architects and Designers Diary, 1985 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Exhibition publications on Matter, [1970s] (Box 12, Folder 3 - 4)
  - Graphis article on Matter, 1980-1981 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Grant applications, 1977 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - "History of Writing" time-line, [ca.1984] (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Letter to Matter's students about his death, 1984 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Letters about "Herbert Matter: A Retrospective" [exhibit at the Art and Architecture Gallery, Yale School of Art], 1977-1978 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Matter's promotional material, undated (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Notes on Matter Memorial Day, Yale, 1984 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Notes on Walker Art Center show, 1989 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Papers on Yale classes, 1972-1979 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Photocopies of items loaned to Alex Matter, 1991 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Photocopies of Matter notebooks from Paris, 1928-1932 (Box 12, Folder 15 - 17)
  - Photograms from class demonstration, 1982
    See: Oversize Folder 2
  - Photographs of bark by Matter, undated
    See: Oversize Folder 1
  - Photographs of exhibition at MIT, [1950-1960] (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - Photographs of Matter, undated
    See: Oversize Folder 3
  - Photographs and postcards (unidentified) (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - Press sheets and mock-ups for Giacometti publication, undated
    See: Oversize Folder 9 - 10
  - Teaching aids [posters of Matter's work created by the Reinhold Book Corporation, [post 1962]
    See: Oversize Folder 11
  - Videotapes of Matter interview
    - Original, Videotape (U-matic) (Box 13)
    - Duplicating master, Videotape (Beta) (Box 13-D)
    - Use copy, Videotape (VHS) (Box 13U1)
    - Use copy, Videotape (VHS) (Box 13U2)
  - "Herbert Matter on trade symbol design"
    - Original, Undated; 1 (Box 14)
    - Use copy (part 1), compact disc (Audio CD) (Box 14Ua)
    - Use copy (part 2), compact disc (Audio CD) (Box 14Ub)
- Oversize
  - Photographs of bark by Matter (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Photograms from class demonstration, 1982 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Photographs of Matter (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Knoll advertising (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Harper's Bazaar cover, 1940 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - New York Studio School posters (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum poster, 1974 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Matter, Alex [poster for The Drifter] (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Press sheets and mock-ups for Giacometti publication (Box 15, Folder 9-10)
  - Teaching aids [posters of Matter's work created by the Reinhold Book Corporation], [post 1962] (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Thirteen Photographs: Alberto Giacometti and Sculptures (Box 16)